{"tossups": [{"question": "An event involving these two countries is the subject of a Quentin Tarantino-produced documentary, <em>Freedom\u2019s Fury</em>. During that event, one participant saw \u201cabout 4,000 stars\u201d after being struck by Valentin Prokopov. Ervin Zador\u2019s face wound nearly led to a riot in Melbourne during a 1956 Olympic water polo match between, for ten points, what two countries, one of which had just had a revolution crushed in Budapest by the other?", "answer": "<b> Soviet Union</b> and<b> Hungary</b> (accept in either order; accept<b> U</b>nion of<b> S</b>oviet<b> S</b>ocialist <b>R</b>epublics in place of Soviet Union) (2) This man was briefly restored to power by Zhang Xun. This man benefited from the Articles of Favourable Treatment, though that was revised following a coup by Feng Yuxiang. Prince Zaifeng ruled as a regent for this man, who was tutored in his early years by Reginald Johnston. This man, who was forced to abdicate at age 6, was the subject of a Bernardo Bertolucci biopic that detailed his path from Cixi\u2019s successor to puppet leader of Manchukuo. For ten points, name this final emperor of China. ANSWER:<b> Puyi</b> (accept<b> Xuantong</b> Emperor)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "During this battle, the ambassador Mikelis was shot trying to board the<em> Guerrier</em>, prompting the<em> Asia</em> to open fire. Prime Minister Wellington sacked this battle\u2019s winning commander, who had controversially provoked a showdown by anchoring his fleet across from the losing side\u2019s horseshoe formation once reinforcements from Henri de Rigny and Lodewijk [lode-veek] Heyden arrived. This battle, which was prompted by the losing side\u2019s decision to reject the Treaty of London, featured an allied fleet under Edward Codrington defeating the Ottoman navy. For ten points, name this decisive 1827 battle of the Greek War of Independence.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Navarino</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s story was popularized in a ballad created by his friend Wallace Saunders. A sound that mimicked a whippoorwill call became identified with this man, who built a six-tube whistle for his work with the Illinois Central. This man told Sim Webb, a fireman, to leap out of their car, saving his life in an accident that killed only this man. For ten points, name this engineer who became a folk hero after heroically slowing his train prior to a collision in 1900.", "answer": "Casey<b> Jones</b> Page 1", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Short Fiction"}, {"question": "Though his mother offered his weight in gold as compensation for his corpse, this man was buried by William Malet. This man\u2019s brother divided his land between this man and Beorn. After a shipwreck, this man was captured and taken to Beaurain by Guy, Count of Ponthieu. This brother of Sweyn won a battle that followed Fulford, and at his most famous battle, this man fought alongside Leofwine. An arrow to the eye legendarily killed, for ten points, what Anglo-Saxon king who was defeated by William the Conqueror at Hastings?", "answer": "<b> Harold Godwinson</b> (accept<b> Harold II</b>; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The<em> Official Bulletin</em> was the daily newspaper of this organization, which released films like<em> Persching\u2019s</em> <em>Answer</em>. A piece created by this organization shows a gorilla holding a struggling woman and contains the caption \u201cDestroy this Mad Brute.\u201d Workers in this organization gave over 7.5 million speeches during the changing of film reels; those speakers were known as Four Minute Men. Posters encouraging civilians to buy liberty bonds were created by, for ten points, what committee that used propaganda to build support for American participation in World War I?", "answer": "<b> Creel</b> Committee (accept<b> Committee On Public Information</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Publius Mucius Scaevola was the last holder of this position to have written for the<em> Annales Maximi</em>, a yearly set of annals published by its holders. While serving as king, Numa Pompilius created this position, whose final holder was a member of the Second Triumvirate alongside Octavian and Marc Antony. Lepidus once held this position, which served a role similar to the<em> rex sacrorum</em>. The title of \u201cGreatest bridge builder\u201d was bestowed on, for ten points, what office that oversaw the priesthood of Roman religion?", "answer": "<b> Pontifex Maximus</b> (accept<b> Greatest Bridge Builder</b> before mentioned; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Elizabeth Lee Hazen and Rachel Fuller Brown named the first antifungal antibiotic in honor of this state. George Soper failed to collect samples from a woman in this state, where Dr. Sarah Josephine Baker\u2019s efforts led to the hospitalization and quarantine of Mary Mallon, who carried the pathogen responsible for typhoid fever. For ten points, name this state where public health officials wrote symbols in chalk on people during six-second medical examinations administered to immigrants at Ellis Island.", "answer": "<b> New York</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man captured the cloth industry of Lille after a decisive victory at Mons-en-Pevele. This man carried out a burning at the stake on an island in the Seine to curb the influence of the Knights Templar, though his conquest of Flanders was set back at the Battle of the Golden Spurs. The Babylonian Captivity began when this man feuded with Pope Boniface VIII, forcing the papacy to move to Avignon. For ten points, name this French monarch who was named for his good looks.", "answer": "<b> Philip IV</b> (accept<b> Philip the Fair</b>; prompt on Philip)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The Freemasonry movement traces its connection to the Knights Templar to a secret act by this man.", "answer": "Jacques de<b> Molay</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In this region in 1965, the<em> Long Shot</em> underground nuclear weapons test was carried out on Amchitka. In 1946, an earthquake in this region destroyed Unimak\u2019s Scotch Cap Lighthouse, which prevented tsunami warnings from being relayed; that disaster inspired the creation of the Pacific Tsunami Warning Center. In June 1942, the Japanese invaded this region\u2019s islands of Kiska and Attu. The Bering Sea and Pacific Ocean are divided by, for ten points, what chain of islands that extends southwest from the largest US state?", "answer": "<b> Aleutian</b> Islands (prompt on Alaska, the north Pacific Ocean, etc.)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "In one work by this philosopher, the drunken Alcibiades bursts in after various luminaries take turns giving speeches about love. This thinker postulated the existence of abstract forms, such as the Good. Another work by this founder of the Academy envisions an ideal city-state and includes the Allegory of the Cave. For ten points, name this author of the<em> Symposium</em> and the<em> Republic</em>, a Greek philosopher who wrote many dialogues featuring his teacher Socrates.", "answer": "<b> Plato</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Jesse Langdon was the final surviving member of this group, which frequently met in the Menger Bar. This group, which was sometimes described as its founder\u2019s \u201cWeary Walkers,\u201d had a 50th anniversary stamp that commemorated the death of its captain \u201cBucky\u201d O\u2019Neill, who had died at Kettle Hill. Alongside the Buffalo Soldiers, this group fought against the forces of Antero Rubin at the Battle of Las Guasimas in Cuba. The 1st US Volunteer Cavalry was the official name of, for ten points, what Spanish-American War-era cavalry unit containing Teddy Roosevelt?", "answer": "<b> Rough Riders</b> (accept<b> 1st</b> US<b> Volunteer Cavalry</b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Richard Gott resigned from an editorial post for this publication after being accused of secretly negotiating with the KGB. Sarah Tisdall leaked information about the positioning of cruise missiles to this publication, which controversially defended the Widgery Tribunal</b> <b>in the aftermath of (+)</b> <b>Bloody Sunday. David Cameron\u2019s role in the Panama Papers was</b> <b>investigated by this newspaper, which broke the news of NSA surveillance programs leaked by (*)</b> Edward Snowden in 2013.<em> The Observer</em> is the sister newspaper to, for ten points, what British daily newspaper that was founded in Manchester and revealed the 2011 News phone hacking scandal?", "answer": "The Manchester<b> Guardian</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This empire was victorious at the Battle of Avarayr against the Armenians, but granted them freedom of religion anyway. During a lengthy peace known as the Intermediate Era, this empire\u2019s Yazdegerd I ended its persecution of Christians. A ruler of this empire</b> <b>allegedly flayed and (+)</b> <b>dyed the skin of his rival vermillion after winning the Battle of</b> <b>dyed the skin of his rival vermillion after winning the Battle of</b> <b>Edessa against Valerian. This empire was founded after (*)</b> <b>Edessa against Valerian. This empire was founded after (*)</b> Artabanus V was defeated by Ardashir. Shapur the Great ruled, for ten points, what Persia-based empire that succeeded the Parthians?", "answer": "<b> Sassanid</b> Empire (prompt on \u201cPersia\u201d or \u201cPersian Empire\u201d before mention) Page 9", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}